hey guys welcome to concept and coding
this is Shan today in the springboard
series we are going to do dependency
injection and before we start dependency
injection I want to tell that what is a
prerequisite for us the prerequisite is
that you need to understand the bean and
the life cycle right which I have
covered in the previous video of this
right there I explained you the life
cycle of a bean so that you would be
able to understand where this dependency
injection actually comes in into the
picture of a complete life cycle of a
being right so if that is clear to you
you would be able to coate so many
things but if you have not seen this
video be and life cycle like I I'm
pretty much sure there are like lot of
doubts going to come okay so with this
base understanding that you already know
the life cycle of a bean I am proceeding
further okay so before we understand
what is dependency injection let me tell
you one problem like let's see the
problem which it tried to solve so there
I created a two very basic class one is
user one is order right user is
dependent on order so that's why it is
creating a new order instance and it's a
Constructor in both very simple class so
user is creating an instance of an order
so do you see any problem with these two
classes the one problem which I see is
that they are highly coupled very
tightly coupled
and because of this tightly coupled two
issue will come the first issue is that
in future any change in the order
structure will bring the change in the
user to for example in the order class
if I'm changing it to this I convert
this order class to an order interface
and I created so many child classes like
online order offline order likewise
because of the future requirement of the
business I have to uh expand this I have
to restructure this order class now
because user class is directly creating
an instance of the order it will get
impact two now this code will not work
because you can't create an object of an
interface so this will break so what you
have to do is you have to change the
code and create an object of a its
concrete implementation so for example
here online order offline order so you
have to create create an object of that
but yeah so this code will work now so
now you are creating an order but now
you are creating its concrete
implementation okay so this is the first
issue that any change in the structure
of order your user class will also get
impact like you see now let's say you
have done this this will create another
issue right it will break the dependency
inversion rule of the solid principle so
what d says in the solid principle the D
says in the solid principle that do not
depend on concrete
implementation rather depend on
abstraction so when you are doing this
new online order you are creating an
object of an concrete implementation you
are actually breaking the dependency
inversion rule of solid
principle so to fix it what you have to
generally do is you have to uh depend on
its abstraction uh interface class in
this case right and its dependency
should come from the external so let's
say that whoever is going to create an
object of user they will pass whether
online order or offline order that will
ultimately get set to here so this is
what dependency inversion principle
says so in Spring
boot this dependency
inversion can be achieved through
dependency injection
okay so dependency injection solves the
above
program so what dependency injection
says that we can make our class
independent of it
dependencies so here in this case user
was uh dependent on order right so we
can make independent of dependencies so
now here if you see that I am not
creating any new order or if even in
interface I not creating new online
order concrete class
nothing right
so there is no tight coupling between
user and order now so this order will
contain let's say in future you have
online order offline order so many
things what actually it will contain
that dependency we haven't put into the
user
class and that responsibility we have
given to the external Source like to
whom like spring so spring will resolve
this dependency but you have make your
classes like very loose
couple okay so how is spring boot
generally uh do uh dependency injection
so you got what dependency injection is
dependency injection is to bring the
loose coupling between two classes or
you can say that of we can make our
class independent of it
dependencies okay and what uh you can
always explain with this example that
these are the problems so dependency
injections helps to achieve this
dependency inversion rule of the solid
principle so now in the same class if we
rewrite through in Spring boot what we
can do is we can create a user class and
create at the rate component means we
are telling to the spring that you
manage the bean of this class we are
creating an order class also put at
theate component means telling a spring
to manage the be of this class now this
user class is dependent on order now
here I'm not creating any object but I
have written an
autowired so what this autowired says
that autowire tells to the spring that
hey first look for a bean of the
required type if order Bean is already
present use that and inject into it
resolve the
dependency if not you will create it and
then inject it first create the bean of
the order and then inject Ed so now what
you're doing is you giving
the responsibility to external Source
what is the external Source a spring so
spring is now using its logic to how to
create an instance of
this through
autowire okay so this I put it just to
so that you can recall that where the
dependency injections comes into the
picture
so this
injection at the rate autowire through
at theate
autowire depend uh
spring inject the dependency into this
field right so there are three ways to
do that one is field injection another
is Setter injection and third one is
Constructor injection very very
important in Industry you will mostly
see that we are using construction
injection
but many of them doesn't know why but we
know that we have to use construction
injection we are don't have to use this
but why so I will explain you the
advantage and disadvantage of
each so first is field injection so
dependency is set into the fields of the
class directly what does it mean so here
if you see this is the class I have
created a user class put at theate
component means now spring has to create
its Bean this is the just a simple
Constructor and I have so this user
class is dependent on this order class
so this order object I needed but I have
tell now spring you create an instance
of this
order so this is an order class I have a
simple Constructor component means
spring has to create its bean I have
just put lazy from the previous video
you might already understand that if we
put lazy means during application
startup this object will not get created
only when it first used then only it
would be created
okay so I I have written it here just
for the sake that this locks would like
totally get sequence like exactly where
it used so I'll tell you now what would
happen field injection so now here if
you see that on this
field I have put this autowire so this
is known as field
injection so what now spring will do so
you know the sequence right when when
you started the application so ioc will
get started so ioc will get started
right so what ioc will see it will look
for all the beans which it has to
initiate so it will look for at theate
component uh classes so it found this
user and order so it will first create a
user user
initiated then it found an order so it
will has to invoke it but it say that
okay it says that lazy I don't have to
invoke it now when it would use I will
use it so user is created now it will
see that okay is there any dependency
which I have to resolve so it will look
for it will use reflection spring uses
reflection to iterate over the fields
and resolve the dependency so internally
spring it uses the reflection and
iterate over all the fields and see that
hey any field has autowired on it if yes
then spring has to resolve its
dependency so now spring find that okay
order is the field which I have to
resolve for this user Bean so now
because of autowire it first check hey
order Bean is already there no we
haven't because we have marked lazy that
order be was not initiated so now at
this time spring will initiate the order
so its order object is created and after
that once the order object is created
that get injected here so now here we
haven't provided at theate configuration
file right so spring will might call its
default
Constructor at theate configuration I
have already explained you in the
previous video so what its Advantage one
advantage is it is very simple and easy
to use so if you just see there you are
just looking at a code you already get
to know know that okay this is the class
this is the field and okay these are the
dependencies I have so it's very very
easy to uh read and understand and it's
very
simple so what is the first disadvantage
of this field
injection one thing is you cannot Mark
as
immutable so what immutable means you
can initialize it once so let's say that
uh a equals to 10 and you marked it as
immutable
final now once it is initialized if you
try to change it value let's say 30 it
say that no you can't change it this is
just an example I'm telling you that
what immutable is means you can
initialize it only once and after that
you cannot change its value so the
disadvantage of uh field injection is
you can't make Fields
immutable you can't do this
you can't put final let's say that your
application has a requirement to make
this order immutable can you do that no
you will put
null so this this issue will
go now what would happen is uh I told
you that spring uses reflection and
during reflection it ignores it whether
it's a final or not and ultimately it
will inject the
dependency so you when you are Ely
trying to use it you won't see null you
ultimately see that the object instance
is injected into it so that breaks
immutability because initially you have
first initialized it with null now as
per the immutability you should not be
able to change its value but since we
are using reflection and you know that
in Java Reflection do not honor anything
it breaks many principles it do not
honor anything so during reflection it
doesn't bother final or not it just take
read this field and inject the
dependency so immutability doesn't
work in the case of field injection
second is chances of null pointer
exception now let's say that you are
creating a user class and you are
creating this object everything is
proper right right you are putting an
auto on this now let's say
some piece of the code creating an
object like new user this is also valid
right nothing wrong in that you can
always create a new object right spring
will not force you that you can't use it
so let's say that some piece of the code
create user create by itself new
user right it will create a new object
so when it create a new object default
Constructor is used so in the default
Constructor what would be the value of
order now
null right because we haven't
initialized it anything now if you try
to call this method user process uh user
object. process so this process will get
invol now it is trying to use the order
order do process order do process and it
will throw null pointer
exception another issue with the field
injection is that during unit testing so
you have this class now you have to mock
this
order right
so now you let's say that what you have
to do is you have to mock this user
object uh order
object so you have created a mock object
of this order now how you will mock it
there is no Constructor here or no
Setter method where you can put this
mock object which you have created into
this because now spring is initially
creating it right you don't have control
over it so how you will set this order
mock into this
class so generally currently today what
we are using is uh mockito and J unit
which we might be using right so there
we put at theate Mock atate inject mock
so what internally it does it it uses
also uses
reflection so it will iterate over it
and it will see that okay if there is
any field order
right so what it will do is it will put
this order mock into that so this at
theate Mock atate inject mock notation
does
that then we have called Setter
injection so Setter injection is that
dependency is set into the field using
Setter method so it means in the setter
method we are putting an auto wire not
on
the member variable field so here I am
not putting autowire
I have just created the field and during
this I have created one set method set
order
dependency like it accept the parameter
order that this dependency it has to now
initialize and put autowire mean that
this method should be used by Spring to
create the dependency inject the
dependency into the
order right so what is the advantage
very simple simple simple as uh field
right uh the same but only instead of
Auto here we are putting an auto
here so what's the advantage Advantage
is that dependency can be changed any
time after the object creation it means
that for now you have dependency let's
say you have put anything since it's a
Setter method right you can always call
this
method pass different dependencies here
and it can be changed let let say you
have order online order offline order
let's say that some other type of order
so let's say you have the privilege now
to first set it through online then
first set it through order offline so it
says that dependency can be changed any
time after the object creation once the
object is fully created spring might
fill the
instance but you also have now leverage
that you can again call this method and
pass whatever you want
maybe if you want to change it okay
second thing is easy of testing so now
in this Setter method in this parameter
you can pass your mock object mock order
object which get set here now you don't
need at theate inject MOX atate Mo which
uses internally reflection you can pass
it and ultimately it would get
set okay but there again it has some
disadvantage one thing is
you cannot make field
immutable like you can't put final over
this why because in the setter method
you are setting it you cannot field
cannot be marked as final because once
user object is created spring will use
the reflection to find out hey is there
any methods which is marked with
autowired it will find it and now spring
would be able to initialize it
right so field cannot be marked as final
here so you will see that here you will
see red line like
this difficulty to read and M so it's
very difficult to read and maintain that
okay hey this somebody created this
field is it managed by a spring or not
so it has to look for any method that
which has Auto on top of it so this is
not readable actually right and it is
very difficult to maintain like okay if
somebody has missed this meth itself or
not so these are the you can say that
the disadvantage of the setter
injection then here comes the
construction injection which is heavily
used or you can say that it's the most
recommended so dependency get resolved
at the time of initiation of the object
itself this is the best part it's not
like after user object is created then
spring uses reflection and then fill up
this in uh dependencies inject the
dependencies no at the time you are
creating a user object itself this
dependencies are also resolved how so
let's say that this is the user class
marked as atate component this is my
order I haven't put at theate Auto here
just a normal order now this is the
Constructor now you know that
Constructor is used
to creating an instance of an object so
in this Constructor you will pass the
order for which dependencies has to be
resolved and here I am setting the
dependency this do order equals to order
and I put Auto wired here so this Auto
wired ultimately get applied to all the
parameters if you have more parameters
like this this Auto get applied to
all so now is spring would resolve the
dependency of all and then initialize it
at the time of user object creation
itself and also one more interesting
will tell you that from the spring
version 4.3
right when only one Constructor is
present then you don't even use autowire
right that is also works fine it is not
mandatory when you have one Constructor
so here if you see that in this user
class I have only one Constructor right
so now when the spring initiated it I
haven't put autowire also so even though
it will work fine and if you have more
than one
Constructor if you have more than one
Constructor then Auto add usage is
mandatory you so now let's say
that I have two dependency on order and
invoice so I've created two classes one
is invoice one is order very
basic right uh at theate component at
the lazy I have just to make sure that
when they should get invoked when
actually they are used so user has this
two
dependency so this is my first
Constructor which resolve this order
this is my second Constructor which
accept the invoice and putting the
invoice now there are two Constructor
and I haven't put an autowire now this
will fail if you start the application
Bean in initiation exception will come
because there is no default
Constructor and after that it has to use
one Constructor but there are more than
one Constructor so spring doesn't know
which Constructor I should use so it
will throw exception that you tell me
like which Bean to use which Constructor
use so you have to tell one autowire on
one of the
Constructor so now let's say I have put
on invoice so what would happen first
user object will get
created so invoice let's say during ioc
started they will find Bean of order uh
class for this but since it's Mar lazy
it will not get invoked till it's not
used so it found user it will now sees
that okay this is the Constructor which
I have to use so now here if you see
that I am trying to use the invoice so
first invoice will get invoke invoice
initialized after that it will put here
invoice injection is set after it says
that user initialization with only
invoice and finish so order is not
even
touched okay so you got the Constructor
injection but now you should ask me that
hey sh why it is recommended what are
the advantages of it so first thing is
all mandatory dependencies are created
at the time of initialization itself so
it makes 100% sure that our object is
fully initialized with mandate
dependency second part is you can make
your field
immutable so now here if you see that I
can use final and in the Constructor you
can initialize it because at the time of
initialization creation of this user
itself I am initializing it only for the
first time after that you won't be able
to change it so this is another big
advantage of it and with Auto on the
field injection I already told you you
can't use final
but with construction injection you can
make your Fields immutable you can put
final and during object creation itself
you can initialize it for the first time
and after that you won't be able to
change
it third Advantage is fail fast means
that if there is any missing
dependency it will fail early so here if
you see that at this point of the time
let's say that I am creating this user
class and I bu mistake missed
autowired when you bu mistake missed
autowired what would happen is a spring
will create an object of this user it
will call the by default Constructor
this order object would be
null and if somebody's trying to access
it like let's say order do something it
will call null pointer exception so you
are getting to know about this at run
time not at compile time but with
Constructor injection like let's say
that even if you missed Auto wire here
like even if you missed autowired on the
Constructor you know that if for one
Constructor spring will automatically
resolve it and fill it if you have more
than one
Constructor let's say then spring will
fail it I told you that it will fail be
initiation exception that which
Constructor to
use right so you have have to first put
Auto wire
somewhere right so it will force you it
will fail fast during compile time
itself unit testing become easy that the
same as the seter injection right like
you have an order object you can inject
it here in the Constructor so I'm
creating new user you can pass the mock
object here you don't need at theate
inject marks at theate Mock reflection
to set the this mock object here in this
you can pass it here it will get
realized so unit testing become little
easy so these are all the advantages of
Constructor injection now you can ask me
that hey sh why you haven't tell me that
what is the disadvantage of Constructor
injection because I will tell you that
the disadvantage of Constructor
injection is also I will consider mostly
as an advantage so one uh generally one
disadv Vantage of Constructor injection
is hey if you have let's say that 20
dependencies your Constructor will
become huge let's say object one object
two object 3 object four like this and
you have put Auto here your Constructor
parameters will keep on increasing so
this is the one of the disadvantage but
here if you see that I considered as an
advantage because this will keep you a
check that
hey is your code design is good that
your parameter you your class has so
many
dependencies I think it's a good time
you should refactor
it so what are the some of the common
issues when dealing with dependency
injection so two major issue is one is
circular and another is your unsatisfied
dependency so let's first see the
circular
dependency so in the circular dependency
what happen is let's say you have a
class order you have a class invoice
order is dependent on
invoice invoice is dependent on order so
now here if you see that this is a
circle circular dependency order is
dependent on invoice invoice is
dependent on order now they are both
using Auto
here so when you start an application
application will fail to start says that
it form a cycle
so this is a circular
dependency so how do you resolve it the
first and the foremost is that we should
refactor the code and remove the
cycle
dependency how there might be some code
here common code which both needed it
take out the common
code to a separate class right and let
those class
classes call those utility class and
that will break your circular dependency
this is your first priority to do that
let's say that if you are not able to do
then the second thing is using at theate
Lazy on autoed an
annotation I have already told you that
if you are
using at theate component if you are
using at theate Lazy over here over the
top of a class
right at the top of the component you
are telling to the spring that during my
application
startup don't create its object eagerly
only when it is required then only
create but now let's say that if you
are putting an auto lazy on top of
autowire not at the top of here what you
are telling to spring so what first is
spring during application stter it would
be able to find at the component
invoice object is initialized so invoice
object is
created and this order object is not yet
initialized so dependency has to be
injected now it will use reflection it
will find okay this field autoi is there
but now it will see that it is marked as
lazy means I don't have to resolve it
now I can put some proxy here right that
after means when the first time it is
used this object then only I will create
the actual object and put it here but
for this at the this time it will just
create some
proxy uh and just add it here right it
won't do a proper
initiation so with the help of this
atate lazy parameter lazy annotation on
top of autowire we can break the
circular
dependency so now first consider this
you will get lazy annotation better
so now here if you see that order I have
marked as lazy right it's a component
invoice has atate component and very
basic so when you start an application
what will start ioc started it will look
for the atate component annotation it
will find both it will say that order it
is marked as lazy so it will not create
its
object now it find an invoice it will
say that okay uh it has to create its
object so invoice initiated so here I
told you that invoice object
initiated now here if you see that it
uses a reflection now it uses a
reflection it will see Auto wir on top
of it and it will try to resolve it so
means now it will create an object of it
one order
initiated so this is how you know that
it works
generally now if I put at theate Lazy
here now what would happen the same
thing first time when you started an
application
like this is lazy so object will not be
created for it first so invoice object
will create
it now this order is not yet initialized
so now it uses reflection it find out
okay this is the auto I have to resolve
it now it also find that at theate Lazy
is there means I don't have to create an
object of it now so it will put it some
proxy but this order object is not
initiated so here if you see that there
is no order initialized
so you got it right whatever uh like how
it breaks the
dependency so that's why we are using
lazy to resolve the dependency so order
is now dependent on
invoice invoice is dependent on
order now at any one of them we put a
lazy right so when you put any one of
them you put lazy you are ultimately
breaking the dep dependency means
because here now it will not create
order object it will just put some proxy
it will not creting order
object similarly in the kind of a field
injection you can use on the seter
injection so like this is the setter at
the rate wired right similarly you can
put it at the setter
also so you can try over the Constructor
injection also so the first is
refactoring second is at theate lazier
anotation on the autowire third is using
post
construct so now what you can do is here
here this is the order
class I have put an invoice this order
is dependent on
invoice so this is an invoice class
right and this is dependent on order now
here if you have seen this I haven't put
autowired
here I haven't put any Constructor
injection or Setter injection I haven't
put anything so I have removed it right
now what you know the sequence being
life cycle right what would happen let
let's say that it first able to uh first
able to find an order right or let's say
it first able to find an invoice
whichever because it can find anything
right so what would happen is let's say
order object would be created let's say
order
initialized so order is initialized So
currently it know that it has to put an
invoice so it will use a
reflection because it has to
to inject the dependency so it has
autowired invoice so now it will say
that hey does invoice B is already
created not yet so it will invoke
it so it will create an invoice
component so now here in the invoice
invoice initialize will come right
invoice initialized will come now here
if you see that I haven't put autowire
here so means order would by default
would be set object would by default
value is null so here order is null but
object creation is successful
now now this object get initialized over
here in
this right and with this one it's being
constructed also completed now in the
post construct you know that post
Constructor comes into the picture after
the dependency injected properly so
dependency injection happened of this
right now post structor will come now
here what I'm doing is hey whatever the
invoice instance you
have I have exposed one Setter method
here whatever the order will come I will
put it here but here if you see I
haven't put Auto wi means I am not
letting a spring do it I am doing it the
the we developer taking the
responsibility application is taking the
responsibility to put the dependency so
I am creating this invoice
object do set order I'm here setting the
order which one this object so this will
also get initialized so this is one
another hacky way of doing it so why I
say hacky because this is generally not
recommended at
all right the first and foremost is
using Code
refactoring all other I consider as as a
hack to make your code works because
something you cannot
change another issue is unsatis
dependency so consider the problem first
so here if you see that this is my user
class user class is dependent on
order order is an interface which has
two child classes online order offline
order now if you have put autowired now
you are telling is spring that hey fill
the dependency
here now how would the spring know that
whether I have to fill the dependency
with online order object or offline
order object which one so when you start
an application it will fail unsatisfied
dependency injection error creating Bean
with the name user it not able to
construct the Bean of a user because it
don't know whether to put online or
offline uh order
object so it has two Solution One is
using at the rate primary
annotation so in one of the online order
and offline order in one of the uh
you can put at marked as one of the
primary you can put a primary
annotation primary annotation tells a
spring that give it a first priority use
it right so we are providing a like say
said some input to the spring that
whenever you find a multiple like what
to use because this is also an order
this is also an order now what to inject
into here use the primary one so it will
use the primary one equals to internally
spring will do new online order it will
call this one online order
initialized right it will say that if
you check its object ultimately it will
get online object
initialized see I haven't put at theate
Lazy here I haven't put at theate Lazy
here that's why at the time of
application
startup this will also get initialized
this will also get initialized this will
also get initialized all three get
initialized but when this dependency is
injected which one it will get injected
this one online order
this because this is Mark as
primary another is using at theate
qualifier annotation so qualifier
annotation means that provide a name so
application will provide a name so on
this online order I have put adorate
qualifier and give some name online
order name something I have
given offline order I have given one
name offline order name so I've given
one qualifier to it now here in the user
class during the order Auto now I have
used
qualifiers okay here qualifiers I have
give offline order use offline
order if you want to change it put
online order so that object will get
created so that also you can use it
using the qualifiers
annotation right
and uh application will start properly
with this so this is everything about
dependency injection at all if you have
any doubt ping me in the comment section
we can discuss more thank you bye